John A. Williams Papers
John A. Williams Papers
1960-1968
Williams, John Alfred, 1925-
3.0 linear ft.
Papers of the African-American author, novelist, poet, and short story writer. Collection includes correspondence (1960-1968), typescript novels, poems, and short stories; and memorabilia, including clippings, photographs, and an audiorecording.
148791
Biographical History
John Alfred Williams, African-American author, journalist and academic, was born December 5, 1925, in Jackson, Mississippi. He served in the U.S. Naval Reserves as a pharmacist's mate in the Pacific from 1943-1946, and earned degrees in English and journalism from Syracuse University. In 1960 he published his first novel, The Angry Ones; this and subsequent novels including the best-selling The Man Who Cried I Am, explore the experiences of being a black man in America.
Over his career Williams worked as a journalist for CBS, Ebony, Jet, and Newsweek, among others. He taught at many colleges and universities, including the College of the Virgin Islands, City University of New York, Sarah Lawrence College, University of California at Santa Barbara, La Guardia Community College, the University of Hawaii, Boston University, and Rutgers University, where in 1990 he was named the Paul Robeson Professor of English. He is a member of the National Institute of Arts and Letters.
In 1970 Williams received the Syracuse University Centennial Medal for Outstanding Achievement, and in 1998 his Safari West won the American Book Award. He retired from Rutgers in 1994.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The John A. Williams Papers consist of correspondence, clippings, memorabilia, writings, and published material.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Writings are arranged alphabetically by title.
Separated Material
Books by Williams have been transferred to Rare Books for separate cataloging. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
African Americans; Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Williams, John Alfred, 1925-; African American novelists.; African American poets.; African Americans -- Biography.; American literature -- 20th century.; American literature -- African American authors.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drafts (documents); Photographs.; Poems.; Authors.; Novelists.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John A. Williams.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1960-1965; 9 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], 1967-1968; 6 folders (Box 1)
  - [General], undated (Box 1)
  - Rejections (Box 1)
- Clippings
  - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Academy of National Institute Awards audiorecording, circa 1962; williams_ja_001; 1 reel, 7 1/2 ips, running time 22:05 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - After me, you (Box 2)
  - Aggie jive (Box 2)
  - [American Negro in Africa] (Box 2)
  - Angry Ones (original title: One for New York)
    - Draft, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - 2d draft, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - 5th draft (Box 2)
  - Another possibility (Box 2)
  - Audio poetry (Box 2)
  - [Big Ralph] (Box 2)
  - Bird (Box 3)
  - Cool one, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Day of the dead cat (Box 3)
  - Eager warriors (Box 3)
  - Flutter of a hawk (Box 3)
  - Kelley (Box 3)
  - Last flight of dreams, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Man who cried I am, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Man who cried I am (Box 4)
  - [Martin Luther King], 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Month in the country: a diary (Box 4)
  - Moody's squad (Box 4)
  - Most native of sons: a biography of Richard Wright (Box 4)
  - NAACP convention, 1959; four reports for WOV (Box 4)
  - Negroes in Pennsylvania, 1-page list (Box 4)
  - Party (Box 4)
  - [poetry] (Box 4)
  - Portrait of a city: Syracuse, the old home town (Box 4)
  - Prisoner (Box 4)
  - Prix de Rome, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Protectors, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Sissie, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Spring song (Box 5)
  - Syracuse: a city in transition (Box 5)
  - This is my country too
    - Edited typescript, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Setting copy (Box 5)
    - Mail (Box 5)
  - Two by John: angry office (Box 5)
  - Two by John: Only an afternoon (Box 6)
  - Why don't you go back where you came from? (Box 6)
  - With regrets (Box 6)
- Published material
  - By Williams, articles (Box 6)
  - By others (Box 6)